Even so, Satoru...
Before, I could only imagine being alone,
本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流，禁止用于商业用途
それでもね　悟
but now I've got a family,
独りぼっちでいることしか想像できなかったあたしが
and it was all made possible
because of you.
更多中日双语字幕，尽在 www.kamigami.org 和微博 @诸神字幕组
今こうして家族といられるのは
Thank you.
Thank you...
悟がいてくれたおかげだよ
ありがとう
What did I do?
ありがとうか…
僕は一体何を…
Okay, okay.
Are you hungry?
よーしよし　お腹空いたの
よしよし
That's right.
I saved Hinazuki.
And after that,
そうだ　僕は雛月を救ったんだ
we tried to make it so that Aya Nakanishi
and Misato weren't alone.
そしてその後　僕たちは中西彩と美里を独りぼっちにさせまいとして…
Yashiro...
I have...
八代…
my memories back!
俺の記憶は…
戻っているぞ
台本
戚风
翻译
Naga
财布酱
君を待った 僕は待った
校对
乙一
戚风
途切れない明日も過ぎていって
时间轴
宋宋
和路雪
压制
VCB-Studio
负责人
戚风
立ち止まって 振り返って
とめどない今日を嘆きあった
記憶だって 永遠になんて
殘らないもんと思い知って
僕はずっと掻きむしって
心の隅っこで泣いた
そしてどうか なくさないでよって
高架下 過ぎる日々を
後悔してんだよってそう言い逃したあの日
君を待った 僕は待った
途切れない明日も過ぎていって
僕は今日も掻きむしって
忘れない傷をつけてるんだよ
君じゃないとさ
ERASED
字幕
诸神字幕组
Good luck!
-Kazu
Fight!
-Osamu
So Kazu is a carpenter...
Good luck!
-Kazu
Fight!
-Osamu
カズは大工なのか
Sounds like both he and Osamu
are working really hard.
カズもオサムも頑張ってるんだな
Yeah.
Come to think of it, Misato said
she was going to pay you a visit.
そういえば　今度美里がこっちに遊びに来るってさ
Really?
そうなの
I thought Misato hated me.
美里には嫌われてたと思ってたけど
This brings back memories...
懐かしいなぁ
Like that lunch money thing...
A lot happened back then, huh?
給食費のこととか色々あったよね
But Misato is the one
who proposed fundraising activities
でもさ　悟の入院費用の足しになればって募金活動言い出したの
to help pay for your
medical expenses.
SATORU FUJINUMA
DONATION MONEY
FOR MEDICAL EXPENSES
to help pay for your
medical expenses.
美里だったんだぜ
I had no idea.
そうだったんだ
You tried to help Misato that day, right?
あの日　悟は美里を助けようとしていた
You remember everything, don't you?
お前　全部思い出しているんだろ
Why didn't you tell us?
何で…言ってくれなかったの
I didn't want to get you involved.
巻き込みたくなかったんだ
It's been 15 years.
あれから15年経ってる　証拠も全てなくなってるし
All of the evidence is gone
and I doubt anyone
would believe my testimony.
僕の証言なんて多分誰も信じない
I was so happy to see you
wake up after 15 years, Satoru.
15年ぶりに目覚めた悟を見て　俺は本当にうれしかった
Nothing could've made me
happier than your return.
悟が戻ってきたことが何よりもうれしかった
That's why I didn't ask you
about the past.
だから　あえて過去のことは聞かなかった
You've fought plenty already,
and I didn't want to jolt you
悟はもう十分戦ったし
傷ついた心と体を癒やしてる悟を揺さぶりたくなかった
when you were healing
your wounded mind and body.
But if you intend to fight alone again,
でも　もし悟がまた一人で戦おうとしているのなら
I want you to take us with you.
俺たちも連れていってほしい
Hiromi has been coming to the hospital
all these years to see you
悟に会うために　病院に通い続けたヒロミは医者を目指している
and now his goal is to become a doctor.
And I became a lawyer.
そして　俺は弁護士になって　今も澤田さんとやつを追い続けている
Even now, Sawada
and I are pursuing him.
You were our hero back then, Satoru.
あの時　悟は俺たちのヒーローだった
Now we understand why we wanted
to catch up to you and fight alongside you.
悟に追い付きたくて　悟と一緒に戦いたくて
今の俺らがある
It was the same
with the stuff about Hinazuki.
雛月の時だってそうだったろ
悟は俺のことを信じて話してくれた
You believed in me then
and told me the truth.
That's why I believed in you.
だから俺も悟のことを信じた
I want to believe you for my own sake.
愛梨の「信じたい」は自分のためだよ
It's the flip side to someone
saying "please believe me."
誰かに信じてほしいの裏返しなんだよ
Airi...
愛梨…
That's right.
そうだった
I have friends I can trust.
僕には信じ合える仲間がいたんだ
The killer is...
犯人は…
Yashiro.
八代だ
I figured as much.
だと思ったよ
When I deliberately tapped my finger
on the wheelchair on the way...
ここに来る途中車椅子を指で叩いてみせた時
わざと反応を殺していたね
...you stifled a response, didn't you?
15年前
15 years ago...
君は僕の計画をことごとく阻止してみせた
you completely ruined my plans.
That was far beyond...
それはもはや…
子供離れしたとかいったレベルを超えた
the level of a child.
It was as if you could see the future.
まるで未来が見えているかのような…
Yashiro!
八代　俺はお前の未来を知ってるぞ
I know your future!
How?
なぜだ　なぜ俺の思考を先読みできた
How did you know what I was thinking?
未来を知っているとはどういう意味だ
What did you mean
by "I know your future"?
You intend to murder me
as soon as I tell you, right?
それを教えたところでお前は俺を殺すつもりだろう
分かっているよ
I know what you're doing.
You've got a cell phone in your pocket.
ポケットの中には携帯電話が入っているんだろう
Are you recording this?
Or are you on the phone with someone?
録音しているのか　それとも通話中？
だとしたら相手はケンヤかな
If so, is that person Kenya?
END CALL
15年前の事件はもう時効だ
What happened 15 years ago
has passed the statute of limitations.
So you want to ask me
about crimes I committed
だから時効になっていない事件のことを聞き出そうと思ったんだろ
that haven't passed
the statute of limitations, right?
でもそんな事件は存在しないんだ
Except they don't exist.
So you can never capture me, Satoru.
だから　悟　君は僕を捕まえることは永遠にできない
Look, you have a text from Kumi.
ほら　久美ちゃんからメールが届いているぞ
Incoming Mail
Kumi
Satoru, thank you
for listening to my wishes.
Kumi's IV drip will start at 4:30.
Incoming Mail
Kumi
Satoru, thank you
for listening to my wishes.
4時半になれば　久美ちゃんの点滴が始まる
Of course, your
fingerprints are on the bag
筋弛緩剤が混ざったその袋には
that has a muscle-relaxant
drug mixed in it.
もちろん君の指紋が付いている
You've led a ten-year-old girl
手術を苦にした10歳の少女を尊厳死に導いてあげたんだ　君は
who was worried about her
surgery to a merciful death.
And feeling guilty about that,
I jump off the roof.
そして　僕はそれを苦にしてここから飛び降りる
You read my mind again,
先読みの種明かしをしたところで　君は自分の命を救うことはできない
though there's nothing
you can do to save your own life.
だけど久美ちゃんの命を救うことはできる
On the other hand,
you can save Kumi's life.
Even if I talk, what guarantee
do you have that you'll help Kumi?
僕が話したら　久美ちゃんを助けるという保証は？
そんなものあるわけがないだろう
There is no guarantee, naturally.
But there is a possibility.
でも　可能性は残る
If you don't talk,
there isn't even a possibility.
話さなければ可能性すら残らない
残念だよ　もう時間がない
Too bad. We're out of time.
これは僕にとってもイチかバチかの賭けだった
This was a sink-or-swim gamble for me.
でも　結局特別な理由なんてなかった
But in the end,
there was no special significance.
全ては偶然だった
It was all coincidence.
僕の未来を知っているなんて言葉もブラフだった
You saying you knew
my future was just a bluff, too.
安心してくれ
Have peace of mind.
I'll leave a few heartfelt
last words to your mother.
お母さんへの遺書は心を込めて書いておくよ
Text
Sachiko Fujinuma
To Mom
Please forgive me for dying before you.
Well, Satoru, I work tomorrow morning,
so I'll see you in the afternoon.
Text
Sachiko Fujinuma
To Mom
Please forgive me for dying before you.
じゃあ　悟　明日は午前中仕事だから午後から来るよ
眠ったべか
Sleeping, huh?
Mom...
母さん
実は僕　記憶が…
To be honest, I have...
...your memories back, right?
戻ってるんだべ
I know. Since Kayo visited you, right?
知ってる
加代ちゃんが来た時だべ
Yokai...
妖怪め…
母さんも加代が来た時口止めしなかったでしょ
When Kayo visited, you didn't forbid her
from talking about it, did you?
Actually, after Kenya and Hiromi left,
ケンヤ君とヒロミ君が帰った後さ
実はちょっと失敗したなって思ったんだわ
I felt like I'd made a mistake.
I thought they weren't able to say
what they really wanted to tell you.
ホントに言いたいことも言えなかったべなって
After seeing Kayo and her baby,
I didn't have the heart to hush her up.
加代ちゃんと赤ちゃん見たら　口止めなんてできるわけないべさ
15年も待って目覚めた悟に会いに来てくれたのにさ
After all, she came to see you
after waiting 15 years for you to wake up.
I saw your face
and talked to you every day,
あたしはね　毎日あんたの顔見て話し掛けてたけど
but when you spoke
and your voice broke,
しゃべり出してあんたが声変わりしてて
I felt like you'd grown for the first time.
「ああ　成長してる」って初めて感じて
I was moved.
うれしかったよ
もう…大人なんだね
You're an adult now.
Mom...
お母さん
I want to take the bull
by the horns and live.
僕は踏み込んで生きていきたい
After all this time,
what are you talking about?
いまさら何言ってんのさ
Before the coma, you always
took the bull by the horns.
あんたは眠っちまう前から　思いっ切り踏み込んで生きてきたべ
Right.
Life is filling up what's missing in you.
足りない何かを埋めていくのが人生
That's what I said when I took charge
of the sixth grade class.
それは僕が6年生を担当した時に話す言葉だ
The day Hinazuki was taken
into protective custody,
雛月が保護されたあの日　雪の中に立つ先生の横顔
I saw your face in profile
reflected in the snow.
一番記憶に残っている先生の顔がそれだった
That is what stuck
in my memory the most.
僕の父親は僕が生まれてすぐにいなくなった
My father left the picture
soon after I was born.
That's why I don't remember
what he looks like.
だから顔はまったく覚えてないんだ
But in that one moment,
you were my father, Sensei.
だけど　あの時の先生は紛れもなく僕の父親だった
You filled the hole inside of me.
先生は僕に空いた穴を埋めてくれた
I've also been waiting 15 years
for you to wake up, Satoru.
僕も悟が目覚めるのを15年間待ち続けた
Ever since you left,
I lost that impulse that defines me.
悟がいなくなって以来
僕は僕が僕であるための衝動を失ってしまったんだ
It's been so long.
本当に長かったよ
But—
だけど…
You're not alone anymore.
もう独りぼっちじゃない
僕たちの決着って何だろう
How do we settle things between us?
The police catch you?
先生が警察に捕まること？　僕が先生に殺されること？
You kill me?
It's already settled.
もう決着はついている
I think I've won.
多分僕の勝ちだ
Kayo Hinazuki, Aya Nakanishi,
Hiromi, Yuuki...
雛月加代も中西彩も　ヒロミもユウキさんも
I saved all of them.
みんな僕が救った
And Mom, whom you murdered
in the future.
未来で先生に殺された母さんも
Murdered in the future?
未来で殺された？
Satoru, what are you...
悟　お前は一体…
I ruined your plans...
先生の計画を阻止できた理由…
because I know your future.
それは僕が先生の未来を知っているから
That's all.
ただそれだけだよ
だからみんなを守れた
That's how I was able
to protect everyone.
だから先生は誰一人として僕に関係する人間を殺せなかった
That's why you weren't able to kill
anyone with a connection to me.
Including myself...
そして　僕自身も
悟　僕はいつでも君を殺せた
Satoru, I could've killed you anytime.
Of course, now too.
もちろん今もだ
You let me live, Sensei.
先生は僕を生かしておいた　15年間も
For 15 years.
Because you needed me!
それは　僕が必要だったから
I was your reason to live.
僕は先生の生きがいだった
I was your hope.
僕は先生の希望だった
I filled the hole in your heart!
僕は先生の心の穴を埋めた
I beat you, Sensei.
先生は　僕に負けた
Wrong!
違う
This time too...
今回も…
I'm gonna win!
勝つのは僕だ
You can't kill me, Sensei.
先生には僕を殺せない
15年は長いよね
15 years is a long time, isn't it?
眠っていた僕にとっては一瞬だったけど
I was asleep, so it passed by
in an instant for me,
but I think 15 years went by
excruciatingly slowly for you, Sensei.
先生にとっての15年はあまりに長かったんだと思う
FUNABASHI GENERAL HOSPITAL
You're alive because I'm around.
先生は僕がいるから生きている
You feel like you're alive.
生きている実感が持てる
僕は何度もこの人生を生き直して
I've relived this life a number of times.
You've murdered a number
of my friends, Sensei.
何人もの仲間を先生に殺されてきた
But right now, I bear you no hatred.
だけど　今は憎しみはないんだ
In this world, the only person
who knows the real you...
この世界で　本当の先生を知ってるのは
is me.
僕だけだよ
That's right.
そうだ
Satoru...
悟
I can't live...
僕はもう…
without you.
君がいなければ生きていけない
You're under arrest
for attempted murder.
殺人未遂の容疑で緊急逮捕だ
PRESCRIPTION INFORMATION
You're under arrest
for attempted murder.
PRESCRIPTION INFORMATION
Is Kumi okay?
久美ちゃんは大丈夫？
Yes.
PRESCRIPTION INFORMATION
ああ　でも八代のことは伝えてない
But we didn't tell her about Yashiro.
PRESCRIPTION INFORMATION
Not with her surgery coming up...
手術も近いし
Right.
PRESCRIPTION INFORMATION
"Believing in someone."
That's a weird phrase, isn't it?
信じるって変な言葉だよな
After all, if you truly
believed in a person,
だって　本当に心から信じてたら　信じるなんて言葉はいらないだろ
you wouldn't need to say,
"I believe in you."
It's like saying, "I believe in air."
空気があると信じてるとかさ
You mean "believing"
because there's doubt?
疑ってるから信じる…ってことか
I don't mean to say that
"believing in something" is like a lie.
だからって　信じてることが嘘っぽいなんて言いたいわけじゃないんだ
"Believing" is really a term
of hope of wanting to believe.
信じるっていうのは信じたいっていう希望の言葉なんだってこと
CHIBA POLICE
I lost my life from the age of 11 to 25.
僕は11歳から25歳までの人生を失ってしまった
But that lost time itself is my treasure.
でも　その失った時間そのものが僕の宝物だ
僕だけがいなくなった街で
In a town only without me,
友達が僕のために人生の貴重な時間を割いてくれた
my friends spent the precious
spare time in their lives on my behalf.
Heroes always come running
in at the last minute!
ヒーローは遅れてやって来るからな
- Here's Satoru!
- You're late!
悟だ
遅いぞ
- Finally!
- Took you long enough!
やっと来た
遅えよ
相変わらずだね　バカなんだから
As usual. Because he's stupid.
A town without me alone...
僕だけがいない街　僕だけがいない時間…
Time without me alone...
That's my treasure!
それこそが僕の宝物だ
Episode 12
Treasure
BOYS' FLIGHT
You're blowing me away!
いいじゃないですか
BOYS' FLIGHT
I love it when you take the bull
by the horns, Sensei.
BOYS' FLIGHT
先生のこのずばっと踏み込む感じ　好きなんですよねぇ
I love it when you take the bull
by the horns, Sensei.
Then I'll keep going in this direction.
じゃあ　こんな感じで進めます
Sorry to have you come all the way here.
すみません　わざわざ来ていただいてしまって
Are you going on a trip?
ご旅行ですか
Yes.
ええ
After this, I'm going back
to Hokkaido to see old friends.
これから昔の仲間に会いに　北海道に帰るんです
Oh, that's right.
そうだったんですね
RECEPTION ROOM
Please have a great weekend.
良い週末をお過ごしください
And I almost forgot!
ああ　そうだ
TO THE KING'S STRENGTH
GATHER FELLOW COMRADES!
GALACTICA SWORD
~7 HEROES~
Congratulations
on the upcoming anime version!
TO THE KING'S STRENGTH
GATHER FELLOW COMRADES!
GALACTICA SWORD
~7 HEROES~
アニメ化決定　おめでとうございます
Right now, I make a living
as a manga artist.
今は漫画を描いて生活をしている
Revival hasn't happened
to me since then.
あれからもう「リバイバル」は起きていない
僕だけが見てた君のこと 過去も未来も
悲しみも喜びも　すべて
SHIRATORI FOOD PRODUCTS
大人になるってきっと
優しくなることだと信じていた
子どもの頃の僕のままに
君のこと
守りたいと思う
YANAGIDA BAR
暗闇から目覚めても
僕を待ち受けてる彼方で
SATORU FUJINUMA
二人を隠したこの街に
誰も知らない雪が降っていた
MIKOTO ELEMENTARY SCHOOL
君は僕の胸に刻まれた一番深い傷跡のようで
Ice Hockey Club 2010
National Champions
君が笑うこの世界の歌
取り戻すよ
Two weeks until the opening
of the 2010 Olympics in Vancouver...
2010年バンクーバー大会開幕まであと2週間に迫った今日
すでに選手村に入っている…
I'm going for a walk.
ちょっと散歩してくる
See you later!
いってらっしゃい
See you later.
いってらっしゃーい
They said we're getting
even more snow this evening.
夕方からまた雪がひどくなるって言ってましたよ
HIGUMA MOVING CENTER
"My Hero" by Satoru Fujinuma.
『僕のヒーロー』　藤沼悟
守りたいと思う
I don't have the courage
to take that first step.
僕には踏み込む勇気がない　だから僕には仲間がいない
紛れもなく暖かい場所があることを信じてる
That's why I don't have
any good buddies.
It's fun playing with casual friends,
友達と遊ぶのは楽しいけれど　きっと仲間は友達とは違う
寂しさに喰われた優しさが
"good buddies"
and "casual friends" are different.
I saw the final episode of my favorite
anime, "Fight, Wonder Guy!" yesterday.
昨日　『戦え！ワンダーガイ』という大好きなアニメの最終回を見た
白い雪に埋もれていく夜
In the first part,
Wonder Guy was fighting alone.
最初の頃はワンダーガイは一人で戦っていた
君は僕の胸に小さな火を灯す古い傷跡のようで
He'd go down again and again
倒されても倒されても諦めずに勇気を出して戦い続けた
but had the courage
to keep fighting and never give up.
微笑んでよ
"If you don't take that first step,
a path won't open for you."
「踏み込まなければ道は開けない」そう言って戦い続けた
この世界の暗闇から
That's what he said
and kept on fighting.
目覚めていく光のような君の歌
Then other people felt his
courage, and little by little,
そうしたらその勇気を感じた人たちが少しずつ仲間になってくれた
became buddies with him.
That's why in the end, even when it looked
like he was going to lose to the bad guy,
だから最後　敵に負けそうになった時も
he never stopped believing
that his pals would come to the rescue.
きっと仲間が助けに来てくれると信じ続けることができた
僕だけが見てた君のこと
でも僕にはワンダーガイみたいな勇気はないし　仲間もいない
But I don't have Wonder Guy's courage
or good friends like that.
So I felt really envious.
だから　とても羨ましいと思った
It made me wish to have true friends,
僕も大きくなったら
friends who trust each other,
when I get bigger.
お互いに信じ合える本当の仲間ができるといいなと思った
BIG WAVE, SMALL WAVE
friends who trust each other,
when I get bigger.
BIG WAVE, SMALL WAVE
Can you believe this snow?
すごい雪ですねぇ
関東でこんなに降るのは10年ぶりだってテレビで言ってましたよ
They said on TV it's the most
the Kanto region has had in ten years.
Can I take shelter
from the snow with you?
一緒に雪宿りしてもいいですか
I never stopped believing.
僕は信じてた
ERASED